Guide to the Oscar Micheaux Society Papers, 1976-2004 RL.00896
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oscar Micheaux Society papers
1976-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oscar Micheaux Society
RL.00896
4.5 Linear Feet
The Oscar Micheaux Society formed in the early 1990s to promote the study of the early African-American film director, writer, and producer Oscar Micheaux. Oscar Micheaux Society newsletters, production files, administrative materials, and correspondence regarding grants, restoration projects, Micheaux-related events and exhibits, and black film scholarship.
3375 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Oscar Micheaux Society Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Historical Note
The Oscar Micheaux Society formed in the early 1990s to promote the study of the early African-American film director, writer, and producer Oscar Micheaux. It released its first newsletter in February 1993 under the editorship of Jane Gaines and Charlene Regester, professors of film at Duke and UNC, respectively. The group would later collaborate with Turner Classic Movies to restore a recently rediscovered print of Micheaux's silent-film masterpiece Symbol of the Unconquered; the restored film aired as a part of TCM's "A Separate Cinema" series in the summer of 1998. The Society also spearheaded a book project entitled Micheaux and His Circle. The collection of essays featured several Oscar Micheaux Society Newsletter contributors, many of whom had presented their work at the "Micheaux and His Circle" conference at Yale in 1995; it was co-edited by Jane Gaines, Pearl Bowser, and Charles Musser.
Collection Overview
This collection contains copies of the first eleven issues of the Oscar Micheaux Society Newsletter, along with files relating to the production of those newsletters. (Beginning with the twelfth issue in 2004, the newsletter was published electronically.) There are several files of proposals, budgets, and correspondence from the many grant applications by which the organization attempted to secure funding for its book and restoration projects. The collection also contains information and programs from a variety of Micheaux-related events and exhibits; newspaper and magazine articles about Oscar Micheaux; resources and scholarship about Micheaux and black film generally; and a large number of photos, stills, and visual materials.
African Americans in motion pictures; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States; Motion pictures -- United States -- History -- 20th century; African American motion picture producers and directors; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Micheaux, Oscar, 1884-1951; Oscar Micheaux Society; Oscar Micheaux Society
- Correspondence, 1990-2000, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Oscar Micheaux Society correspondence, including extensive e-mail exchanges between the newsletters editors and contributors.
  - Barbara White correspondence, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Campaign to nominate Ben Rinaldo to the Hollywood Walk of Fame, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Dorothy Dandridge photo correspondence, 1998 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Micheaux book correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter correspondence, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
  - Pearl Bowser/Charlie Musser correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Press correspondence, 1998 (Box 1)
  - TCM Micheaux restoration correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - William Greaves correspondence, 1994 (Box 1)
- Events, 1976-2001 and undated, 1 box
  Programs, guides, and information from a variety of Micheaux-related events, some of which (such as the "Micheaux and His Circle" conference) were sponsored and organized by the Society.
  - American Museum of the Moving Image guide to exhibitions and programs, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Black Filmmakers Hall of Fame, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Carolina Theatre Black Film Festival, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Early Black Film Festival (Germany), undated (Box 1)
  - Festivals/Series, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Gregory, SD welcome binder, 1996 (Box 1)
  - John Hope Franklin 80th birthday celebration, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mapp Collection of African-American Film Posters exhibit, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - "Micheaux and His Circle" conference, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - "Micheaux and His Circle" conference curriculae vitae, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Multicultural Film Festival, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Oscar Micheaux Film Festival, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Oscar Micheaux Film Festival, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Oscar Micheaux Film Festival, 2001-2005 (Box 1)
  - Oscar Micheaux Society annual meetings, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - The Other Oscars (Great Bend, KS), 2001 (Box 1)
  - Race Reels poster, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Symbol of the Unconquered screening at Duke, 1998 (Box 1)
  - TCM's A Separate Cinema, 1998 (Box 1)
- Grant Applications, 1992-1997 and undated, 1 box
  Proposal guidelines and drafts, budgets, and correspondence related to the Society's grant applications.
  - Academy of Motion Pictures Arts and Sciences Foundation, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Book proposal and budget, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Budgets, proposals, and correspondence, 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation grant, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
  - Grant application drafts and correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Grant proposal template, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Louis B. Mayer Foundation, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Micheaux and His Circle budgets, 1993 and undated (Box 1)
  - Micheaux Project funding ideas, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Micheaux Project restoration leads, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities/American Film Institute grants, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities grant, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania grants, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Rejection letters, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Returned proposals, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
- Micheaux Publicity, 1983-2003 and undated, 1 box
  Newspapers, magazines, and clippings about Oscar Micheaux, black film generally, and the Society's activities.
  - News Articles, 1983-1998 and undated (Box 2)
  - Newspapers, 1994-2001 (Box 2)
  - Periodicals, 1998-2003 and undated (Box 2)
- Newsletters, 1993-2003, 1 box
  Eleven printed issues of the Oscar Micheaux Society Newsletter.
  - Newsletter Vol. 1, Feb. 1993 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 2, Nov. 1993 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 3, Summer 1994 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 4, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 5, Summer 1996 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 6, Winter 1997 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 7, Summer 1998 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 8, Spring 2000 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 9, Spring 2001 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 10, Fall 2001 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 11, Fall 2003 (Box 2)
- Production Files, 1992-2004 and undated, 2 boxes
  Files related to the production of the Oscar Micheaux Society Newsletter, including article ideas, drafts, correspondence, and layouts. This series also includes files related to the production of a special edition of Black Film Review that Jane Gaines and Pearl Bowser curated.
  - Advertising, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Article ideas and submissions, 1995-1997 and undated (Box 2)
  - Black Film Review, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Chapel Hill Printing and Graphics, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 1 production files, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 2 production files, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 3 production files, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 4 production files, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 5 production files, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 6 production files, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 7 production files, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 8 production files, 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 9 production files, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Vol. 10 production files, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter Vol. 11 production files, 2001-2003 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter Vol. 12 production files, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
  - Stationary, undated (Box 3)
- Resources, 1979-2003 and undated, 1 box
  Filmographies, bibliographies, catalogs, and listings relating to the life and career of Oscar Micheaux, as well as many resources relating to black film generally.
  - African-American Film Collection transfers, undated (Box 3)
  - Afro-American Studies at Duke, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Alaska Center for Documentary Film, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Articles and papers, 1979-1992 and undated (Box 3)
  - Available Visions conference participants contact sheet, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Black film A/V resources, undated (Box 3)
  - Black press bibliography, undated (Box 3)
  - Blacks and the West, 1996 and undated (Box 3)
  - Black Arts Research Center, undated (Box 3)
  - Black-cast films at the Library of Congress, undated (Box 3)
  - Black independent film information, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Blockson collection, 1989 (Box 3)
  - British Film Institute Happy Though Married, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Cinemaction: Le Cinema Noir Americain, undated (Box 3)
  - The Girl from Chicago script transcribed by Sergio Mims, 1996 (Box 3)
  - International Film Archive information, undated (Box 3)
  - Ku Klux Klan, undated (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress and Smithsonian Video rare silent film brochure, 1994 (Box 3)
  - List of available Micheaux films, undated (Box 3)
  - List of black-cast film producers and titles, undated (Box 3)
  - Micheaux bibliography and filmography, 1997 and undated (Box 3)
  - Micheaux biographical documents, undated (Box 3)
  - Micheaux films and novels, 1992-1997 and undated (Box 3)
  - Micheaux web resources, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Midnight Ramble information, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Norman Film Company filmography and visuals, undated (Box 3)
  - Rhapsodies in Black exhibit program and bibliography, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Smithsonian Institute Traveling Exhibition Service, 2001-02003 (Box 3)
  - Translation of La Negra draft, undated (Box 3)
  - The Tyler, TX Black Film Collection, undated (Box 3)
  - W.E.B. Du Bois Institute at Harvard University, undated (Box 3)
  - Wolfsonian Museum (Florida International University) information, 1995-2003 (Box 3)
- Scholarship, 1998-2001, 1 box
  Copies of articles and essays on Micheaux.
  - A Pioneering Black Filmmaker by Scott Heller (Chronicle of Higher Education), 1995 (Box 3)
  - The Outcome of that Discontent by Sarah Weiss, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Stranger in a Strange Land by M.K. Johnson (Western American Literature), Fall 1998 (Box 3)
  - Without the Gates by Fiona Barnett, 2001, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Subscriptions and Membership, 1993-1998 and undated, 1 box
  Subscriber lists, subscription forms, and mailings.
  - Accounting, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
  - Mailings to members, 1996 (Box 3)
  - New subscribers, 1994-1998 and undated (Box 3)
  - Subscription forms, undated (Box 3)
  - Subscriber lists, 1994 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials, 1992-2000 and undated, 1 box
  Photos and stills for use in the Oscar Micheaux Society Newsletter or in the essay collection Oscar Micheaux and His Circle.
  - Black film stills, undated (Box 3)
  - Contributor photos, 2000 and undated (Box 3)
  - Micheaux's grave, undated (Box 3)
  - One More River to Cross cover, undated (Box 3)
  - Oscar Micheaux and His Circle visuals, undated (Box 3)
  - Photo rights correspondence, 1998-2003 (Box 3)
  - Photos/visuals, 1992-1993 and undated (Box 3)
  - Schomberg Center stills, 1998 and undated (Box 3)
  - Stills, undated (Box 3)
  - Xeroxed visuals, undated (Box 3)
  - Xeroxes of stills from the African Diaspora Images collection, undated (Box 3)